<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disclaimer and answer of the Commons of England, of and unto a scandalous libell, lately published against the Parliament, and espcially the House of Commons and their proceedings: intituled The remonstrance of the Commons of England to the House of Commons assembled in Parliament, and falsely suggested to be preferred to them by the hands of the speaker. Wherein the malicious cavills and exceptions by the libeller taken to the proceedings of Parliament are detected and summarily answered, and the sottish ignorance and wicked falsehood of the libeller cleerely discovered, and the justice of the proceedings of this Parliament and House of Commons evinced and manifested.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E100_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859199</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859199</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83701)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E100[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disclaimer and answer of the Commons of England, of and unto a scandalous libell, lately published against the Parliament, and espcially the House of Commons and their proceedings: intituled The remonstrance of the Commons of England to the House of Commons assembled in Parliament, and falsely suggested to be preferred to them by the hands of the speaker. Wherein the malicious cavills and exceptions by the libeller taken to the proceedings of Parliament are detected and summarily answered, and the sottish ignorance and wicked falsehood of the libeller cleerely discovered, and the justice of the proceedings of this Parliament and House of Commons evinced and manifested.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
                  <author>White, John, 1590-1645, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIII [1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 4.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111268:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCLAIMER AND ANSWER OF THE COMMONS OF <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> Of and unto a Scandalous Libell, lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed againſt the PARLIAMENT, and eſpecially the Houſe of COMMONS and their Proceedings: INTITVLED <hi>The Remonstrance of the Commons of <hi>England</hi> to the Houſe of Commons aſſembled in PARLIAMENT,</hi> And falſely ſuggeſted to be preferred to them by the hands of the Speaker. WHEREIN The malicious Cavills and exceptions by the Libeller taken to the Proceedings of PARLIAMENT are detected and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily anſwered, and the ſottiſh ignorance and wicked falſehood of the Libeller cleerely diſcovered, and the Juſtice of the Proceedings of this PARLIAMENT and HOUSE OF COMMONS evinced and manifeſted</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> M.DC.XLIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111268:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111268:2"/>
            <head>A Diſclaimer and Anſwer of the Commons of <hi>England</hi> to a ſcandalous Libell lately publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, and eſpecially the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and their proceedings, intituled, <hi>The Remonſtrance of the COMMONS of ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E the Commons of <hi>England</hi> doe not prejudge but upon imature deliberation had of the ſaid Pamphlet, and of the Contents thereof, doe righteouſly judge and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Authour thereof to be no true ſonne of our mother, but ſome baſtard of <hi>Rome</hi> and brat of a <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> his ſpirit bewrayes him and his language, which is of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> and not of our <hi>Canaan;</hi> belching out the poyſon of an envenomed and rotten heart in blaſphemies againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the mother, nurſe and onely preſerver of our Religion, Lawes, Liberties and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts under God, and againſt the Houſe of Commons, which hath ever been the faſteſt friend to this Kingdome, and the happineſſes thereof, and againſt this now Houſe of Commons and Parliament, which hath prevented more miſchiefes from, and procured more good to this Kingdome and our neighbour Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> then any former: Of which we ſhall ſhew our ſelves to be infinitely unworthy and unthankfull for, if we ſhould not vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate them, and their fidelity: and might juſtly expect for ſuch neglect to be delivered over unto the extreame tyranny, and the miſerable effects of it, which firſt by ſubtilty and cunning workings in a clandeſtine way, and now forcibly by the Sword and hand of Violence is endeavoured to be brought upon us and our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and which we had been before this overwhelmed in, but that the Lord hath made them his bleſſed hand to prevent and keepe off the ſame. And when we perceived this Devill incarnate to hide
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111268:3"/> himſelfe, and vent his impious blaſphemies under our name, of whom we are very confident he never harboured a good or honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thought, or regarded us more then the dung of the Earth, but for his own baſe and accurſed ends we could not be ſilent leaſt we ſhould betray our innocency, and be thought to be ſuch as he is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Object.</label> The firſt thing we meet withall in this Libell, is, <hi>That the Authour counterfeits himſelfe to be a Phyſitian, and pretends a great cure, and propounds ſpeciall preparatives unto it. The firſt ſpeaking in our names to the Houſe of Commons, he affirmes us to be ſtill, the true body of the Commons of</hi> England, <hi>and they but the preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> And in this he ſhews himſelfe to beds groſſely ignorant, as he is wickedly malicious, for the Houſe of Commons is a part of us, and the choice moſt excellent and principall part too, and not only our Repreſentative, and are intereſſed and ſharing in the publike good and evill as much as any, and more then moſt of us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Obj. 2</label>. He ſaith, <hi>We have not ſo delegated our power to the Houſe of Commons, as to make them the Governours of us, and of our Estates, and that in truth they are but our Procurators to ſpeake for us in that great Councell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> This is a fuller diſcovery of his ſottiſh ignorance, for he knows nothing of the nature of Parliaments, that knows not that the Houſe of Commons is abſolutely intruſted with our perſons and eſtates, and by our Lawes inveſted with a power to diſpoſe of them as they ſhall thinke meet, not onely by making new Lawes, but alſo as they are a great Court above all our ordinary Courts, to governe us, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of all things proper to the power and juriſdiction thereof in all things tending to the conſervation of the Common-wealth and of our Religion, Laws and Liberties, and to be limitted to be only Proct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors to ſpeak for us is ſenſleſſe and ridiculous.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob. 3</label>. He ſaith, <hi>That in right we ought to have acceſſe to thoſe whom we have choſen as there ſhall be cauſe to impart our deſires unto them, and that they ought not to refuſe us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We never found our ſelves denied in any matter to impart our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111268:3"/> deſires to that Honourable Houſe petitioning them in a fitting manner, when our Petitions have concerned the good, peace or ſafety of the Kingdome, things belonging to their juriſdiction: but if any of us have petitioned for matters of a private nature of right or wrong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween particular perſons, or in any way or manner not beſeeming, we hold it fit ſuch Petitions ſhould be refuſed, and they ought not to be heard, much leſſe accepted that ſo much forget themſelves and their duties.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> He ſaith, <hi>That by involving our Votes in theirs, we had no purpoſe to make the Commons Houſe of Parliament perpetuall Dictators.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We ever had a purpoſe and conceive it neceſſary to the good of the Kingdome, That the Parliament continue together and remain undiſſolved, untill all the Grievances of the Kingdome be redreſſed and all things in the Kingdome reformed, and this we believe was and is by the conſtitution of this Kingdome, an undoubted Right and Priviledge of Parliament, for to that end we choſe them, and are to maintaine them; and for that end they are called to doe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto thoſe things, which by them are to be ordained in and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the difficult and urgent buſineſſes that concern the King and the State, and Defence of the Kingdome, and of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as by the Writ of their Election appeares<note n="a" place="margin">Book of Entries Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t § 1.</note>. And certainly the late practiſes of our Kings (among other Incroachments and Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theirs) to diſſolve Parliaments before they have done vvhat they are called for, and ſetled all the buſineſſe that concerne the State and Defence of the Kingdome, is againſt the originall Conſtitution and end of Parliaments and Rights of the Subject, and hath induced great Miſchiefes, and almoſt Deſtruction and ſlavery upon this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, eſpecially when the ſame have been diſſolved, becauſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their duties and the truſt repoſed in them by the Kingdome, they have endeavoured to reforme the oppreſſions done by colour of the Kings perſonall Command againſt Law, and contrary to the Kings Oath and Office, and have been made uſe of onely to burthen us with Subſidies and Taxes, and not to eaſe us of any unjuſt burthen or impoſition. And if this worke for which the Parliament was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111268:4"/> called were once perfected, notwithſtanding the Act of continuance of this Parliament (which was made by this Bablers aſſent, if he be an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man or Subject of <hi>England,</hi> and he party to it) we are confident the Parliament would gladly aſſent to a diſſolution of it, their attendance upon the publike ſervice being extreamely burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and prejudiciall to their private eſtates and advantages.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob. 5</label>. He ſaith, <hi>That we never intended that the Houſe of Commons ſhould have ſuch a latitude of power, as to imbarke us all in a civill warre to the deſtruction of us and of our poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> When we choſe our Knights and Burgeſſes for the Parliament, we entruſted them with all the power we could inveſt them withall, to doe whatſoever in their wiſdome they ſhould thinke meet, and to uſe all meanes, even warre or whatſoever ſhould to them ſeem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient or neceſſary for the ſafety or preſervation of our Religion, Lawes and Liberties, and we hold it infinitly better to endure for a time a civill warre, and the effects of it, then to looſe our Lawes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Religion, and with our poſterity to be inſlaved perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the perſonall wils of our Kings, and to the baſe ſpirits of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Councellors that pervert and ſeduce them from their people. We never received prejudice from any free Parliament, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Kingdom hitherto, but we have in all ages ſuffered from our Princes, when contrary to their Oath, Office and truſt, they have followed their perſonall wils, and forced the illegall iſſues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon us, and forſaken or neglected the Lawes and the counſels of Parliament, and we never found any meanes to relieve us againſt ſuch ſufferings, but by our Parliaments, which as we reſpect the happineſſe of our ſelves and of our poſterity, we will love and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here unto.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob. 6</label>. He ſaith, <hi>We were further off from having any thoughts, that by any of their Votes they would or could draw us into any acts of diſloyalty or diſobedience againſt our naturall liege Lord, to whom by the laws of God and man, we owe and will pay allegiance and fidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We could never heare of—neither doth this falſe Libeller expreſſe any particular Vote of the Houſe of Commons, by which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111268:4"/> any man can be juſtly ſaid to be drawne into any act of diſloyalty or diſobedience againſt the King, if he had we ſhould have bin able to give our ſence of it. But the deceitfull are converſant in Generals.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen and conſidered his preparatives, and by it we ſee what Phyſitian we have, if this Mountebanke ſhould be entertained, that ſo impudently thruſts himſelfe into office before he be called. Now let us follow this wild-Gooſe on in his chace: Who next<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offers divers things to the conſideration of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Object.</label> And firſt he ſaith, <hi>We are reſolved with our lives and fortunes to maintain the true Proteſtant Religion, eſtabliſhed by the lawes in our Church, and to maintaine our well ſetled government under a Monarchy, according to the Knowne Lawes of this Land, and to maintaine the juſt Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of our Parliament, without which our Lawes can hardly be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, and in aſserting of this, we have the daily Proteſtation of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and His Majeſties Declaration; and we hold our ſelves bound in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to his Perſon, and in Chriſtianity to beleeve, that he will faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully performe his word with his people, and that we have this further aſsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof, that he hath deſcended ſo low from his Throne, as to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſome errours, that have ſlipt him in his paſt government, and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake not to give way to the like hereafter, and that we wiſh that the Houſe of Commons would with the ſame Ingenuity acknowledge their errours and amend them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> This man though he aſſume our Name is farre from our ſenſe. We dare not limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the holy Scriptures is the adequate object of our Faith and Religion and not our Lawes, and if any thing concerning Religion be eſtabliſhed by our Laws, which is not warranted by the holy Scriptures, or that is defective and comes not up to the perfect rule of Gods Word, we deſire our Laws may be amended by the Parliament, and all the Worſhip of God and Diſcipline of the Church, formed in all things according to the patterne given of God, leaſt the divine Curſe lye upon us and our Land, for adding to the Word or diminiſhing ought from it; and the Scriptures reject every thing in the Worſhip of God meerely for this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111268:5"/> cauſe, becauſe he hath not commanded it, becauſe it never came into his mind, and countes it vaine Worſhip, vaine Inventions, if it be mens precepts or not part of his Law<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 19.5. Lev. 10.1 Mat. 15.9. Pſal 119.113. Deut. 12.32.</note>: Secondly, we cannot allow of the Epithite given to our Lawes, limiting them to knowne Lawes; for be they knowne or unknowne to us, we leave the declaring and determining of them to Courts of Juſtice, eſpecially the moſt high Court, the Parliament, and this is certainely knowne Law, and hath ever beene ſo: The King hath beene in all Ages held and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by our Lawes ignorant of them, as we for the moſt part of us are, and therefore were never by our Lawes intruſted with it. And it is neither Law nor reaſon; That Delinquents againſt the Law ſhould expound or declare the Law, as now adayes they preſume to doe; for if that ſhall be permitted, they would be ſure to eſcape: There is certainely a Snake hid under this greene Graſſe, knowne Lawes; for our parts we reſolve with our lives and fortunes, to maintaine our Religion according to the Word of God, the only rule and judge of it, whatſoever our Lawes be concerning it, for ſo our God hath commanded; and to maintaine our Lawes as they are or ſhall bee declared and determined in our Courts of Juſtice, the onely certaine way to know them by, and not to allow of any thing our King or Delinquents ſhall pretend to be Law, though the ſame be ever ſo much cried up for knowne. And we are as covetous to have Reall ground to confide in his Majeſties Proteſtations as any can be, and are onely troubled and ſhaken, that we cannot ſo fix upon them as we would, by the wayes of government and actions, that under theſe Proteſtations from the beginning of his Majeſties Reigne hitherto have run and doe runne cleane contrary unto them. Can the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Maſſe and Maſſe-Prieſts againſt the Law in the Queenes Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and elſewhere, and the open exerciſe of that abominable Idolatry now in <hi>Redding</hi> every day, and in <hi>Yorke,</hi> and the permitting of the holy Scriptures to be burnt in contempt of God under the Gallowes and elſewhere in <hi>Redding,</hi> the Arming of Papiſts and confiding in them, and the perſecuting of the ſtrictneſſe of Religion under the Names of Puritans and Round-heads, conſiſt with the maintaining of the true
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111268:5"/> Proteſtant Religion. Can the Illegall taxes, Impoſitions, Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, Pillaging, Plundring, conſiſt with the maintenance of the Lawes, Liberties and Properties of the Subject? <hi>Quid verba audio cum ſacta videam.</hi> We ſhould receive more ſatisfaction in our Kings amending his Errours acknowledged, then we can in his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of them, and perſiſting in them, yea increaſing them not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his acknowledgements.</p>
            <p>And for the ſuppoſed Errours of the Houſe of Commons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Malice of this fellow ſcrapes together all that be can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be Errours of theirs, and Malice is ever the fulleſt accuſer: We will proceede to conſider and examine them, and if any ſhall appeare, we are confident the Houſe of Commons will not only ingeniouſly confeſſe, but ſpeedily amend them, becauſe we have ever found them really and actively ready and carefull to amend Lawes paſſed by them, and all other things wherein any ſlip or errour hath happened.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Object.</label> Firſt he ſaith, <hi>that under colour of advancing Religion, incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement is given to Anabaptiſts, Browniſts and all Sectaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If to accuſe ſo generally and incertainely ſhall ſuffice, no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſhall eſcape this malitious envious tongue: Where, when, or how is this incouragement given, or by whom? If he meane the Houſe of Commons as he would inſinuate, we cannot receive his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation; for if by the Apoſtles rule we be not to receive an accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt an Elder under two witneſſes, much leſſe may we receive it againſt ſuch a Senate of Elders, upon the ſingle teſtimony of this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, whom we find a lyer or deceiver in all he ſaith. Secondly, We are not ignorant that the Sects he mentioneth, were fomented and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied in this Kingdome in the time of the reigne and late extreame tyranny of the Biſhops, to vexe the Puritans (under which nick-Name they included all that made any conſcience of their wayes) on the one ſide, as the Papiſts were cheriſhed and increaſed to vex them on the other ſide; for theſe Sectaries being taken and brought from their Illegall Conventicles to the High Commiſſion Court in great heards and droves, found favour, and were with ſome ſlight reproofe or pecuniary Mulct let goe, when a conſciencious painefull
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111268:6"/> Miniſter, if he could not ſwallow a Ceremony themſelves proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med indifferent, was ſtript of all he had, caſt into perpetuall priſon and deſtroyed. Thirdly, We know it doth not belong to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Houſe of Commons to meddle with theſe Sectaries, there being an ordinary open way in inferiour Courts of Juſtice to puniſh ſuch Sectaries, namely in the Kings Bench, and at the Aſſizes and Seſſions. Fourthly, We know alſo, that what the Houſe of Commons can doe for the ſuppreſſing of theſe Sects, hath beene done by them; for firſt, they have paſſed a Bill for a Conſultation to be had with Learned Divines, about ſuch a Church government and diſcipline, as is agreeable to the Word of God, to the end that thereby all Sects may be ſuppreſſed, and we know where it lyes; and in the meane time they have declared and Voted againſt them, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe how hatefull they are unto them, and how ſeriouſly they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and intend the ſuppreſſing of them, as <note n="a" place="margin">Pag 659.</note> appeares in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Secondly, he ſaith, <hi>That under pretence of hatred of Popery, the Booke of Common-prayer, which is eſtabliſhed by Law, is cried downe by many, and all decent Orders in Gods outward Worſhip, and every man left to the dictate of his private ſpirit, and he would have the Lawes againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Sectaries to be put in due execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We obſerve that where the Libeller dares not charge the Houſe of Commons plainely and directly with ſo groſſe a lye as cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe the Booke of Common Prayer, he doth maliciouſly and wickedly inſinuate it; Wherefore elſe doth he mention it among the things which he ſuggeſts to be Voted, Ordered and Acted by them. And the puniſhment of ſuch as cry it downe wee know belongs to the Juriſdiction of the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, not to them. But in regard that the Biſhops themſelves have agreed there are many things in that Booke fit to be reformed, and that tender conſciences are to be eaſed of ſome Ceremonies mentioned in it, the Houſe of Commons have thought it to be very unfit that the ſeverity of the Lawes concerning it ſhould be preſſed, before the aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines have met and ſetled it in ſuch a manner as may be inoffenſive
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111268:6"/> and more agreeable to holy Scriptures; and the rather, becauſe it cannot be cleerely proved what Booke is eſtabliſhed by Law, the Booke which was eſtabliſhed and annexed to the Act of Parliament of 5. and 6. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. to which Booke the Statute of 1. of the Queene referrs, being taken off the File in the firſt Yeare of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> by Act of Parliament, and deſtroyed or loſt, and ſo no Booke remaining of Record, and the Bookes in print ſo differing among themſelves, that which is the Booke eſtabliſhed by Law cannot appeare.</p>
            <p>And for decency in Gods outward Worſhip, whatſoever is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be ſuch by man, and not by the Spirit of God in his Word, is the dictate of a private ſpirit, <note n="a" place="margin">2 Pet. 20.</note> and mans inventions in Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are abominable unto God, who is not pleaſed with the deviſes of our hearts, but reſerves it peculiarly unto himſelfe, to teach us how to worſhip him both inwardly and outwardly, and we deſire that all voluntary Religion and will-worſhip and humility, <note n="b" place="margin">Col 2.23.</note> not directed by Gods Word (in which onely we have his minde made knowne <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.16.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by our Prophet <note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1.18. Act. 3.22.</note> the Lord Jeſus) though it have the colour of our Law, may be cried downe, caſt out and removed according to Gods will, leaſt he ſay unto us when we preſent our worſhip before him, <hi>who required theſe things at your hands?</hi> Eſa. 1.12.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Thirdly, He ſaith, <hi>That under the colour of regulating the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Courts, and taking away the High Commiſsion Court, all ſpirituall Inriſdiction for the Coercive part therof, which is the life of the Law, is taken away, ſo as now no hainous crime inquirable by theſe Courts can be puniſhed, no Hereſie or Schiſmes reformed, no Church can be inforced to be repaired, no Church Officers compellable to take upon them their Offices or performe their duties, no Parſons or Vicars can be inforced to attend their Cures, or give ſatisfaction for the paines of them that doe; No tithes or other Church duties can be recovered by their Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Our deſire is that the Parliament would be pleaſed not onely to regulate Eccleſiaſticall Courts, which were abuſed to the pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our eſtates, and inſlaving of our perſons, as well as the High Commiſſion Court, though in a different degree, but that their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in cauſes Matrimoniall and Teſtamentary, and concerning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111268:7"/> Tithes, repairing of Churches, and intermedling with Church Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers uſurped upon the Temporall law, ſhould be wholly taken away and reſtored to the Common Law, and that Non-reſidency, Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Parſons and Vicars, and neglect of their Cures ſhould by ſome good Lawes to be made, be made inquirable and puniſhable in the Common Law Courts, where we ſhall find certaine and ſpeedy Juſtice, with eaſe to our purſes, and without great travell to our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and not be conſumed and tired out with endleſſe chargeable ſuites concerning them as we have beene in thoſe Courts, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding remaine in the long runne uncertaine of Juſtice. And for matters in their owne nature meerely and onely Spirituall, as Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we deſire ſome better courſe ſhould be ſet for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of them according to the Word of God, and not by the Popes Canon Law; and we partly perceive by the Bills that have paſt both Houſes of Parliament, that they not only intend, but had long before this ſetled all theſe things by their wiſedomes in the beſt way, if they had not beene hindered by men that hate to be reformed; the fault this Libeller would inſinuate to be in the Parliament, lies not in them, but in others that are of the ſame ſpirit with this falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fourthly, He ſaith, <hi>That under the Name of reforming the Church governement, the Parliament endeavoureth to take away the function and very being of Church governours, as Biſhops, Deanes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſo to take away at once the preferments of Learned men and incouragements of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: Let the abuſes be taken away, but not the good uſes alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We beleeve this may be as well objected by the Pope, his Cardinalls and ſhavelings, as for Biſhops, Deanes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall honours and poſſeſſions are greater, and by them held the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and very beings of Church governement, and the preferments of Learned men, and the incouragements of Learning: but we deſire all theſe functions and beings of governement, being abuſes and equally branches of the Man of ſin, the Popiſh Hierarchy and Babell that muſt fall, may be taken away roote and branch out of the Church, as they be out of other reformed Churches: And that the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111268:7"/> Goſpell-Biſhops, painefull Preachers of the Goſpell, that give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to prayer, and the adminiſtration of the Word<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 20.28. &amp; 6.4.</note>, may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all the parts of their function and office, which theſe uſurpers have a long time deprived them of; And that the maintenance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by theſe Idle ſlow bellies, may be diſtributed among the Churches officers ordained by God, worthy of double honour, which will be preferments for Learned men that ſhall make uſe of their Learning for the ſaving of ſoules, the higheſt and moſt noble im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of it, and incouragement to all true Learning.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fiftly, He ſaith, <hi>That for rectifying Church diſcipline and ſome things in Doctrine alſo, an Aſsembly of Divines is propounded to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocated and conſulted with: The matter is right but the manner amiſſe, for the Divines are not nominated by Divines, who can best judge of their abilities, which is the Legall way. The greateſt part of thoſe who are Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, are knowne or juſtly ſuſpected to be perſons ill diſpoſed to the peace of the Church, and addicted too much unto Innovations, and the Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Lay men, are to be the only Iudges of what ſhall be propounded and determined. The Divines are but their Aſsiſtants, and the King is totally to be excluded from having any voice or hand in it, and as it is propounded, it is to be a perpetuall Convocation if the Houſes of Parliament ſo pleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> This cavill might have been made to the Reformation of our Doctrine, in the beginning of the Raigne of Qu. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> wherin if the conſultation had bin with Divines, named by Divines, there ſhould never have been any Reformation at all, the legall way had prevented the divine way of Reforming this Church, the Divines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then univerſally corrupt in Doctrine, as they now be in diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Have not the eares of our Divines univerſally been ſo filled with <hi>Lauds, Whites, Wrens</hi> and their complices, clamours of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops government by <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and their hearts corrupted with a hopefull expectation themſelves might climbe up into the Chaire, as they are ſcarce patient to admit a queſtion to be made thereof, and is it in ſuch a time and cauſe reaſonable to leane the Reformation of Diſcipline and Church-government upon ſuch deceitfull Reeds? will they not pierce the hand, and deceive and delude us? And when our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111268:8"/> freſh experience in the laſt Convocation, informes us what a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miſery was like to have befallen us, had not this Parliament by the good providence of our God prevented it, by Divines nominating Divines, when both the Electors and elected are birds of a feather, like <hi>Ieremies</hi> bad figgs, exceeding bad; ſhall we now againe deſire ſuch a choice? We conceive it is better never conſult with, never chooſe Divines then give way to ſuch elections or nominations. If Divines be choſen, and thoſe godly and learned, that we hope will by their debates endeavour to ſearch out Truth, and love and imbrace it found out, and not ſeek themſelves, what matters it by whom they be nominated? And when we find the Houſe of Commons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to judge of and diſcover the inabilities, defects and errours of the laſt Convocation Divines choſen by Divines, and to convince them of their folly and wickedneſſe, ſhall we queſtion their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to judge of the abilities of Divines, and their fitneſſe to nominate them to conſult of Diſcipline and Government of the Church? And that the Divines nominated by the Parliament, are ill-diſpoſed to the peace of the Church, we verily believe is a falſe, groundleſſe Accuſation, and if this man know any ſuch, he ſhall doe a very good office to name them, that they may be put out of this great imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And for their being addicted to Innovation, we feare it to be true of ſuch of them, as have given teſtimony thereof, in their gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way and yeelding unto the tyranny of the Biſhops in their late Innovations, preſſed without and againſt Law upon the Miniſters, and we know there are many ſuch nominated to be of the Aſſembly. But we conceive the Parliament have in their nomination and choice done, as thoſe that deſire to have the truth, and the beſt way of Church-government and Diſcipline found out, in that they have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men of very different judgements and opinions concerning the ſame, and as neare as they can honeſt men that will ſubmit to truth diſcovered and heaten out by debate and diſpute among them. And though this man call the Parliament Lay-men, we know though they be not in orders, they are in the language of the Scriptures, as much Clergy-men, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Lords lot, portion</hi> and <hi>inheritance</hi> (as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111268:8"/> word ſignifies) as thoſe that are in orders, and we find by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they can judge of Church-government and Diſcipline, and of the reaſons and grounds upon which Divines found their judgement concerning them, as well as Divines can and better too then our Convocation Divines, and ſuch as they have been members of the firſt great Councell at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 15.</note>, and of all great Councels in ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox times. And the concluſion and reſults of the debates concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Church-government and Diſcipline, being to be ſetled for Law by Act of Parliament, the Houſes of Parliament muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be Judges thereof, and that the King is excluded, without whoſe Royall aſſent the Act cannot be of force, is as ſenſleſſe an Aſſertion, as it is groundleſſe, and ſo is his Suggeſtion that this may be a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Convocation, when the Divines are to conſult of a few ſpeciall matters only, and report their Concluſions and reaſons to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and then to end, which cannot be a worke of many weeks or months at moſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Sixtly, He ſaith, <hi>That under the colour of freedom of preaching, ſeditious Sermons are preached daily in the hearing of many of the Houſe of Commons, who traduce the Kings ſacred Perſon, ſlander his Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in expreſse tearmes in courage the maintaining and continuing of this unnaturall and unchristian warre, and yet none are puniſhed for it. Which makes him feare that this is and long hath beene made by ſome, to be the principall engine to kindle this fire of hell to the juſt ſcandall of all good men and ſlander of our Religion, this Doctrine comming ſo neare to that of the</hi> Jeſuites.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If there were any truth in this charge, and this man were gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any good ſpirit, he would rather turne Informer againſt ſuch Preachers and hearers in a right way by complaining of it to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or either Houſe, as well, yea—rather then inſert it in this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, and in ſuch a generall manner without certainty or particularity, and we believe the Sermons thus clamoured againſt are printed, for moſt, if not all, preached before the Houſe of Commons, or in the Church where many of them uſually heare, are publiſhed, and of theſe we can judge and muſt conclude, that this report of them is a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111268:9"/> loud lie, like the reſt of this fellows ſcandalls. Indeed we know that many wicked Prieſts, Malignant againſt the Parliament, and the good and ſafety of the Kingdome have preached ſundry ſeditious Sermons tending to the maintenance and continuance of this unnaturall and unchriſtian civill-warre againſt the Parliament, and excepting ſuch and others of the like ſpirit, as this Libeller is, we are confident there is no man, eſpecially if he love the King and Parliament, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires there may be an honourable end and buriall of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob. 7</label>. <hi>Divers worthy and painfull Preachers have been committed to priſon by the Houſe of Commons for delivering their conſciences freely and religiouſly, and preaching obedience to their Soveraigne. Theſe things tend mainly against the maintenance and propagating of the true Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If this man had informed himſelfe of the cauſes for which Preachers have beene committed by the Houſe of Commons, by the Articles exhibited and proved there againſt them, he could not be ſo wicked, as we conceive, as to publiſh ſo notorious a lie, as this is: For we find upon ſearch, that the Miniſters by them committed have publickly preached to ſtirre-up the Subjects to ſedition, to take up Armes againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and to corrupt the King and us with the leaven of falſe flattering Doctrine, of abſolute Power in the King, to doe what he liſt with us, our eſtates and lives, to puſſe-up the King above what is meet, and to draw us into a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and conſcientious ſlavery; Doctrines deſtructive to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and contrary to the conſtitution thereof and our Lawes, and contrary to Gods command given us, <hi>to ſtand fast in the liberty wherof he hath made us free,</hi> Gal. 5.1.</p>
            <p>And conſidering the endeavours of the Houſe of Commons to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Papiſts, Biſhops, and ſcandalous Miniſters and other rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh that hindred the prapogating of the true Proteſtant Religion, and to plant faithfull, orthodox, painfull labourers in this Church, which is ſo notorious to us all: Malice it ſelfe cannot deny, but that their waies tend unto the maintenance and propagating of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111268:9"/>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Secondly, touching the maintaining the Lawes, hee charges the Houſe of Commons with theſe particulars. Firſt, <hi>That they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves power by a bare Vote without Act of Parliament to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound or alter a Knowne Law, where that Houſe formerly aſſumed no ſuch power, but in order towards the making of a new Law, nor did the Houſe of Peeres challenge any ſuch thing, but they having the power of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory as Iudges have proceeded according to the Rules of the</hi> Knowne Lawes, <hi>and upon their Honours are anſwerable for the Iustice of their Iudgements, as other Courtes are upon their Oathes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> It is plaine that this fellow erres through groſſe ignorance of the proceedings of Parliament, and of all the Records thereof, in which there is nothing more frequent and familiar in all Ages, then to find the Houſe of Commons declaring the Law, and complaining that the King hath done things againſt the Law. Firſt, Judging and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining by Votes, and then claiming the Lawes and the Rights of the people and of their Houſe, and the Lords in like manner, and that in generall, as well as particular caſes, and not to leade the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der—at this time higher; This appeares in the Petition of Right, wherein the Commons firſt declare, and expound the Lawes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe Rights therein claimed and uſurped upon by the King. 2. The Lords joyn with them in that Declaration. And laſtly, the King gives his Aſſent to this Declaration, before and without which theſe things were Law (the Statute being declaratory of former, not introductive of new Law.) And the Kings Aſſent was had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtop the mouthes of cavilling Court, and Innes of Court Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants and Flatterers (the Moth of Kings and Kingdomes) againſt thoſe Laws, and the reſt of this charge is a groſſe lie, and groundles imputation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob. 2</label>. He ſaith, <hi>That the Parliament makes their owne Orders and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to be as Law, and compell them to be obſerved, and with a ſtricter hand, which may bind their Members, but not have the force of Laws till by the Kings Aſſent they be confirmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Beſides the two cauſes here admitted, that they may make
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111268:10"/> binding Orders. Firſt in order to making of new Laws. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, To bind their owne Members; it is moſt evident that the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Ordinances of Parliament are binding and are to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Firſt, where they are in purſuance of the Lawes in being, for to them principally belongs the care of preſerving the Lawes, and of inforcing obedience unto them, and of giving ſtrength and vigour unto them by the King and his ordinary Judges and miniſters of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice neglected or abuſed. Such was the late Order of the Houſe of Commons for the pulling downe of <hi>Cruciſixes</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Images,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. and 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">ti</hi>. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. revived 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Iac. Cap.</hi> 2. And againſt <hi>Innovations in Religion,</hi> impoſed upon the Subject againſt Law, as <hi>bowing at the Name of Ieſus,</hi> which is idolizing a Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God, and without any Law of man, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their own ſouls, and endeavour to deceive others, that pretend they doe it to worſhip the Perſon of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> for if that were a reall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and true, they would worſhip him repreſented by any other name, as <hi>Christ, Saviour, Meſſias, Sonne of man,</hi> &amp;c. and to ſay it is in their liberty to worſhip him under one name and not another, is as groſſe a deceit, and pronounces it—a will-worſhip and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, an invention of man which God abhorres, as I have ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſo indeed they worſhip their owne fancy and invention, and not the perſon of Chriſt, whoſe worſhip muſt only be according to his own rule. And laſtly, they may make Orders and compell obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto them, that are for the ſafety, defence and preſervation of the King and Kingdome<note n="*" place="margin">They be choſen <hi>ad faciendum &amp; con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiendum his quae co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigerint or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinari ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per arduis &amp; urgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs regem ſtatum &amp; defenſiore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regni ac ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clefiae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>nent.</hi>
               </note>; The very words of the Writ by which they be called (not to trouble this ſhort Treatiſe with any more) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts and proves this moſt clearly.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Thirdly, He ſaith, <hi>The Houſe of Commons takes themſelves ſo farre above the reach of the Lawes, that by their Orders and Ordinances, they injoyne the Iudges and miniſters of Iuſtice to forbeare, contrarie to their Oathes, to proceed in their ordinarie courſes, when they pleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We are troubled more with the ignorance and folly of this man, then with any knotty matter of difficulty to anſwer his ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pamphlet. We have obſerved that for a ſuperiour Court to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111268:10"/> and prohibit the proceedings of an inferiour Court, is as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as <hi>Ergo</hi> in the Univerſity Schooles, and Judges and miniſters ſo enjoyned or prohibited are bound by their Oathes to ſurceaſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and the Houſe of Commons have done this in all Ages, and is clearly a Court Superiour to any inferiour, and the Judges and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of inferiour Courts are under them by Law, and to obey the commands and injunctions of the Houſe of Commons to them, is that which the Law requires, and their Oathes oblige them unto.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fourthly, He ſaith, <hi>The Parliament makes an Ordinance to put the</hi> Militia <hi>of the Kingdome into ſuch hands as they pleaſe to conſide-in, without the King, and expreſſely againſt his Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>That they poſſeſſe themſelves of the Navy-Royall, and appoint Admirals, and other Officers by Sea without the King, and uſe the Ships a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, <hi>That they take the Castles, Forts and Ports, and places of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtrength in the Kingdome, and keepe them against the King himſelfe, and this will appeare to have been done by deſigne, for the pretence at firſt was the preſervation of the Kingdome againſt ſome forraigne enemies, where none have appeared for many moneths, and ſuch in truth never were, and by meanes hereof, a warre for the Parliament against the King himſelfe was raiſed for the preſervation of the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Such as have any knowledge of the Conſtitution of this Kingdome, which is a Politicke, and not an abſolute Monarchy, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but diſcerne the apparant ignorance and malice of this Accuſer. In this Kingdome <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Iohn Davies</hi> rep Epiſt. fol. 2. <hi>Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines regni</hi>
               </note> the people originally agreed Laws, ſuch as they found by experience to be good for them, which were therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Cuſtomes of the Kingdome, Cuſtomary Law, Common Law, not impoſed upon them by Charters of Princes, or by Act of Parliament, but aſſumed by them upon their experience of the fitnes of them for them, and are not written as Charter and Parliament Laws be; then they choſe one from among them to be their King for the defence of their Lawes, bodies and goods, and for theſe purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes only they gave him power to governe them, and he cannot go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne them by any other power or rule<note n="a" place="margin">Forteſ de leg. Ang. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>; and for the preſervation of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111268:11"/> the Lawes againſt the Incroachments of the King and abuſe of his power and truſt, which through humane frailty or evill and wicked Councels and flatteries of Court Paraſites, he might fall or be drawn into; and for the making of ſuch new Laws, as ſhould be requiſite; And for the better preſervation of the peace and ſafety of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they ordained a generall and great Councell of the whole Kingdome, anciently called <hi>Michel Simoth, Michel Gemot, Wittenage Mote, magna Curia,</hi> the great Court, commonly called the <hi>Parliament</hi> or the <hi>Common-Councell</hi> of the Kingdome, and inveſted them with all power for the good of the Kingdome and people, and ordained, that the making of new Laws by them for honours ſake, the Kings Royall aſſent ſhould be given unto them; and for this purpoſe they ordained the King ſhould take an Oath to preſerve the Laws and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne by them, and aſſent to ſuch new as his Parliament ſhould find to be for the common good and ſhould tender unto him<note n="a" place="margin">Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of Parl. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>May,</hi> 1642 and reply of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the anſwer thereof.</note>. And between an abſolute Monarchy and this Politick there are theſe differences.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In an abſolute Monarchy the Kings perſonall will is the Law, and his perſonall Command to be ſubmitted unto to doe it or to ſuffer willingly what puniſhment he pleaſes to impoſe for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, which is not a power fit for any but God, whoſe wiſdome is infinite, and will infinitely holy and good, who cannot erre, nor do any wrong, and from whom proceeds no command that is not for his peoples good, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.24. &amp; 10.13. <note place="margin">Soveraign power of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> But the Politick Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall Command or will, if it be not according to the Law ought to be diſobeyed and rejected; and if any ſhall inſtrumentally ſerve ſuch perſonall will to puniſh him that ſo diſobeyes, he that is ſo offended by ſuch officious ſervant of the Kings may have his remedy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Recompence for ſuch injury, and the Kings perſonall illegall command ſhall not afford his inſtrument any protection or defence<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.10, 11, 12. God will puniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to ſuch il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</note>. This is ſo obvious to any verſed in our Laws, or obſerving the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry practice of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ordinary Courts, as nothing almoſt can be more.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An abſolute Monarch cannot be controlled in any thing he doth by his Subjects, but a Politick Monarch may by the Laws diſtributed in his Courts be controlled, and his actions, if againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111268:11"/> Law, defeated, made void, and nothing more uſuall in our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Courts of Juſtice, then to overthrow his Pattents and Grants, and to diſcharge Subjects impriſoned by his Command; and for the Houſes of Parliament or either of them, being extraordinary Courts to overthrow and make void all his illegall Acts that have bin carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-on with abuſed power, to the prejudice of the publike, with which the ordinary Courts durſt not meddle, or were by baſe cowardiſe and feare betrayed to comply withall, as in the caſe of <hi>Ship-mony, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, Knighting money,</hi> &amp;c. And if that Politick Monarchy ſhould by wicked Councels beſeduced to do or attempt things dangerous to the ſafety of the Kingdom, the Parliament ought to complain of them unto him in a mannerly and reſpective and honorable way, and if that take not effect they ought to take care that the Laws and peace and ſafety of the Kingdome be preſerved, not only without, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſonall will: So <hi>Bracton Fol.</hi> 34. <hi>If the King ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a bridle,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>ſhall not governe according to his Lawes, the great Court of his Parliament ought to bridle him:</hi> And ſo Parliaments have often done, as both our Hiſtories and Records of Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly teſtifie<note n="*" place="margin">See the book enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The treachery and diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, An abſolute Monarch chooſes what Councellours he will, but the Politick Monarchs great Councell for the weighty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and urgent buſineſſe of his Kingdome is in greateſt part choſen by the people, and the reſt have it annexed to their honours conferred or deſcended, as the Houſe of Peeres, and theſe are not his Councell only, but the Councell of his Kingdom and people.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, An abſolute Monarch hath the Forts, Ports and Ships of the Kingdome, to uſe and diſpoſe at his pleaſure. But our Politick Monarch hath none of theſe, but in truſt for the uſe and good of the Kingdome, to take order they be uſed, kept and imployed for the good peace and ſafety of the Kingdome according to Law, and not to the hurt or endangering of the ſafety or peace of the Kingdome, as is clearely manifeſted and proved in the Declaration of Parliament concerning <hi>Hull</hi> 25. <hi>May,</hi> 1642. And in the Reply to the Anſwer therof, and more particularly and largely in M. <hi>Prinns Soveraigne Power of Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111268:12"/>
            <p>5. An Abſolute Monarch hath the <hi>Militia</hi> of his Kingdome and Monarch in his owne hand and pleaſure, as in truth, the Lives, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and the Whole of his Subjects are. But a Politick Monarch hath no power to compell his Subjects to find Arms, or ſerve with Arms, except they be bound thereunto by Tenure or Contract, and then, but as their Tenures oblige them, and can only compell his Subjects that have Armes, to ſhew them in Muſters before his Commiſſioners, as appeares cleerely in the Declaration of the Parliament concerning the Commiſſions of Array lately Illegally granted, ſo far is our King from having power over the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome without the conſent of his Parliament.</p>
            <p>And there having beene a manifeſt deſigne to alter Religion and the very conſtitution of this our Politick Monarchy, by a Malignant party prevailing with his Majeſty, diſcovered by the wiſedome of the Parliament, and ſo far carried on, as in a manner all was become ſubject to will and power, and the Laws neither a defence of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons nor of our rights, and our Judges inforced againſt their Oathes and duties to comply with them; and theſe Vipers finding the whole mould of their helliſh devices to be likely to be broken, and Lawes to be made for the eſtabliſhing of our Liberties and propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, and vindicating thereof, and a through Reformation of the Church, in Worſhip, diſcipline and government to be ſet upon and reſolved by the Parliament; they endeavoured to get all the ſtrength of the Kingdome into their hands, <note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> advice in his Letter to the King.</note> and to that end perſwaded his Majeſty to poſſeſſe himſelfe of the Ports and Forts, places of ſtrength (as they called them) that they might without feare of being brought to Juſtice for their delinquency by the Parliament, have acceſſe unto him to advance their ſaid deſigne; and ſeduced the Queene out of the Kingdome, and raiſed Armes by open force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament to deſtroy it, and therein all our Religion, Lawes and Liberties, and drive the King to owne and take all thoſe things upon himſelfe, and forged all the falſe colours and gloſſes upon thoſe helliſh proceedings of theirs, that Jeſuited devilliſh wits can invent to deceive the people, and to draw them to become Felons
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111268:12"/> and deſtroyers of themſelves. Was there not juſt cauſe, and was it not high time for the Parliament, to take care in ſuch caſe, that the Kingdome ſhould be ſet in a Poſture of defence, and that the Ports, Forts, Magazeenes and Ships ſhould be ſecured for the Peace, ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and good of the Kingdome? Was this done by deſigne? ſurely if this had not beene done, we had all ere this beene over-runne with tyranny, and we and our Poſterity made ſlaves. When the King refuſes to doe his duty, which by Oath and Office he is bound to doe, and imploys any thing he is intruſted withall by his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the publike prejudice of him, his Poſterity and Kingdome: It is neceſſary, yea juſt and Legall, that the Kingdomes repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, the great Court, the Councell of the Kingdome, ſhould ſeiſe upon, ſecure and uſe the ſame to the publike defence and for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good, and prevent the Kings ſatisfying the baſe luſts of a few wicked Councellours and Sycophants, that would raiſe themſelves on the ruines of the Common-wealth. And though many parts of the Kingdome have been waſted and grievouſly ſpoiled by forraigne Enemies, of which there are very many in the Kings Armies, brought from beyond the Seas in great numbers, and though we have felt their heatheniſh and barbarous cruelties, this fellow would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us they never appeared. And though the preſervation of the Kingdome againſt forraigne Enemies were one cauſe of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments taking the Forts, Ports and Ships into their hands, power and diſpoſition, yet that was not the only cauſe as appeares in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration<note n="*" place="margin">Declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Martij.</hi> 1641. And the Ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the Militia.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Eightly, he ſaith, <hi>That they who refuſe to joyne in this Warre with the Parliament, or to contribute unto it, they plunder as Malignants and ill affected to the Commonwealth, although he ſees not how it can be leſſe then Treaſon againſt the King to joyne with the Parliament therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We verily beleeve the wayes of the Parliament to be very juſt, and full of reaſon, and Legall, to inforce them that have Eſtates and will not help to quench the publike fire kindled in the Kingdome by the Enemies thereof, nor to preſerve the Parliament which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves their Religion, Lawes, Liberties and all from tyranny and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111268:13"/> violence, with ſome ſmall part of it; and to judge them Malignants and Enemies of their Countrey. Did not the Inhabitants of the County Palatine of <hi>Dureſme</hi> when the <hi>Scots</hi> had broken in upon them, to redeeme their Countrey from plunder and ſpoile, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with the <hi>Scots</hi> for 1600 Markes, and breake open the Cheſt of <hi>William Heburne,</hi> and take 70. pound from him by force in ſuch a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, for the publike ſafety, to help make up the ſumme, when he would not let them otherwiſe have it: and was not this judged law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by all the Judges of the Kings bench in a Writt of Errour brought <hi>Mich.</hi> 14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>Rot.</hi> 60. and a Legall plundering: and other plandring the Parliament never commanded or countenanced. And though this fellow, blinded with Malice, cannot ſee it to be leſſe then Treaſon to joyne with the Parliament in this War, yet ſuch as have any underſtanding in the Laws, know that to joyne with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Court in executing the Proceſſe thereof, to bring Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents to Juſtice with the greateſt force and power of men, if it cannot be otherwiſe done, is lawfull, though the King joyne with theſe Delinquents in reſiſting the ſame, and endeavour to protect them againſt it; and that it is ſo far from Treaſon, as that it is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in ſuch as raiſe Force againſt ſuch Proceſſe, and to protect ſuch Delinquents from the Courts of Juſtice, as was judged in Parliament in the cauſe of <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Yorke, Robert de-Leere</hi> Duke of <hi>Ireland</hi> and others, in the time of <hi>Rich.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. and confirmed after by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in the firſt Yeare of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Ninethly, he ſaith, <hi>That to all the Commanders and Officers of their Army, the Parliament gives large and even profuſe entertainement and rewardes, but out of our purſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We doe not beleeve, neither can this falſe accuſer prove this charge, that any other entertainements or rewards have been given by the Parliament, then were given by the King before this War, nor ſo much as the King hath given ſithence; and what is here imputed to the Parliament falſely, may juſtly be ſaid of the Kings Army, who have free booty, and we are delivered over as a prey unto them, who make the Proverbe that goes of the Great <hi>Turke</hi> true in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:111268:13"/> That where he ſets his foote no graſſe will grow; where the Kings Army goes, they take away Plow and Cart-horſes, cut the Harneſſe, and uſe all the wicked cruell meanes they can to deſtroy Tillage, and bring in a famine and the miſeries attending it upon us.</p>
            <p>Further for the Liberty of our Perſons and proprieties of our eſtates, this Libeller objects that we have little hope of this.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Firſt, <hi>Becauſe the Parliament takes away the Kings Treaſure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepteth his Revenue, poſſeſſeth his Houſes of acceſſe, and pretend all is for his owne ſervice; and if any attend or aſsiſt him, they are condemned as Malignants, Popiſh, Evill Councellours and enemies to the State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> To this we muſt anſwer for the Parliament; That if they had taken any of the Kings Treaſure, the King now upon his Articles of Treaty, wherein he demands ſatisfaction for all he hath any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or pretence to demand of them, The King would have deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, but he demands no ſuch matter, by which this ſeemes to us an apparent, groſſe, lying imputation, and we cannot judge better of it. But we heare of the Jewels of the Crowne, with which the King is but truſted, and which by our Laws are to goe with the Crowne in Succeſſion, that they are imbeſſel'd and ſould away, a dangerous effect of the evill Councells given unto his Majeſty. Secondly, for his Revenue, it is true they have ſeiſed on ſome part of that for the neceſſary maintenance and ſupport of his owne Children, whom he hath left in the power of the Parliament, and to them the ſame hath been diſpoſed, according to the proportions of allowance his Majeſty hath alwayes ſet out for them, and in no other, and without it they might have ſtarved otherwiſe; and if they have ſeized upon any more of his Revenue, it is not conſiderable in quantity, nor fit they ſhould let him have that to maintaine his War againſt his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and people, which is his, only for the publike good, protection and ſafety of his people, and by our Laws ought to be ſo imployed. Thirdly, for his Majeſties Houſes, we know none the Parliament hath medled withall but the Caſtle of <hi>Windſor,</hi> and that is before anſwered, in what hath been ſaid concerning the Caſtles and Forts of this Kingdome. Fourthly, for condemning ſuch as attend, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111268:14"/> him, it is not true, that any one of his attendants, that are bound by ſpeciall ſervice to be with him, have been meerely for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as Malignants, Popiſh, Evill Councellours, or Enemies to the State, but ſuch as having no ſpeciall oeconomicall obligation to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, or have aſſiſted him in this unnaturall War, or are Popiſh, or give him wicked and deſtructive Councell, and foment this War, and Viper-like endeavour to rend out the bowells of the Countrey that bare and nouriſhed them, have been and are juſtly accounted Malignants and Enemies to the State, and their courſes evidence them to be ſuch to all indifferent lookers on, or that ſhall heare any true report thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Secondly, he ſaith, <hi>That the Houſe of Commons, have by Meſſages endeavoured to perſwade our Bretheren of</hi> Scotland <hi>to joyne with them in their Rebellion against their Soveraigne, and that by Votes of their Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If this Libeller had once proved by any reaſon or Law, that any thing done by the Parliament, in oppoſition of the Kings preſent courſes againſt his Parliament and people were Rebellion; he had laid ſome foundation whereupon he might have preſumed to build ſo bold an inference, but neither he nor any other that we have ſeen or heard of, hath as yet been able to doe that: And the Politick conſtitution of the Kingdome is cleerely againſt it, and the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done by our Brethern the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt his Majeſties like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with them, hath been by his Majeſty and the Parliament, judged and declared to the World, in an Act of Parliament made lately, to deſerve no ſuch Imputation, and that Judgement and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration this Libeller himſelfe (if he be an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi>) is a party to, though now he give himſelfe the lye. If our Bretheren the <hi>Scots,</hi> in taking up Armes and coming into this Kingdome ſo armed, and taking the Fort and Port of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> and <hi>Timnoth Caſtle</hi> into their poſſeſſion, to maintaine their Lawes, Religion and Liberties againſt the wicked Councellours that induced his Majeſty to endeavour to infring the ſame, were well done, and nothing therein done amiſſe; let all the world judge of the proceedings of our Parliament in the ſame caſe: <hi>De ſimilibus idem iudicium:</hi> And whom have the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111268:14"/> called in to their aſſiſtance? ſurely no Forraigners nor Papiſts as the King ſeduced by evill Councell hath done, but our Bretheren, intereſſed in the cauſe as well as we, and of the ſame Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Thirdly, he faith, <hi>The Parliament did a greater Act of barbarous hostility against the King in his owne Perſon, and excuſes it, by ſaying it was not their fault, but the Kings and his Councellours, that he went in Perſon into the Battle, which he did with that Kingly courage at will adde to his honour and their ſhame while the World endures, which action of theirs is become odious to God and man, and their excuſe for it ridiculous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If the King ſhould appeare in Armes, to hinder the Juſtice of his Inferiour Courts, were it an act of barbarous hoſtility, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the Proceſſe of ſuch Court notwithſtanding, and would it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue Kingly courage, or adde to his honour, or the ſhame of the Court that awarded that Proceſſe? would it not rather argue a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did diſtemper unbecomming the meaneſt Subject, and be a blot and reproach to him in all ages? If this be ſo in caſe of an Inferiour Court, how can it be an honour to the King, to be found in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that reſiſts the Proceſſe of the Higheſt Court, and Force raiſed by it, to ſubdue and bring to Juſtice the Delinquents againſt the ſame and againſt the Kingdom which that Higheſt Court repreſents.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fourthly, he ſaith, <hi>That as if the Parliament hath ſhaken off all ſubjection, and they become a State independent, they have treated by their agents with Forraigne States; Such an uſurpation upon Soveraignty, was never yet attempted in this Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We conceive, that if the King deſert his Parliament, his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament without him may doe any thing, yea every thing conducing to the good and ſafety of the Kingdome, and Parliaments have done greater matters then this in ſuch caſe, as any verſed in the Hiſtories and Records of this Kingdome well knowes. None ſo bould in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting lyes as this fellow; certainely upon a Machivilian confidence, that men will beleeve rather then examine his falſhoods: beſides his partiality is manifeſt; That he mentions not the Kings uſurpation upon the Soveraigne power of the Three Eſtates from which his power is derived, and to which it is ſubordinate, and the immediate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111268:15"/> iſſues thereof, our Lawes, even from the beginning of his Reigne hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, being ſeduced and miſguided thereunto by wicked Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, in good part ſet forth in the Parliaments Declaration of the State of this Kingdome; the miſchiefes and miſeries whereof we have abundantly felt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fiftly, he ſaith, <hi>The Houſe of Commons command their Orders, and Ordinances, and Declarations to be printed and publiſhed with priviledge, but if any thing come from the King, which may truly inform and diſabuſe the people, they forbid it to be publiſhed, and commit them to priſon that doe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> The Houſe of Commons in ſuch Commands, doe nothing but what is juſt and fit, being their own Declarations and Acts; and for the things that come from the King, we find they come to abuſe the people; witneſſe the <hi>Mercurius Aulicus.</hi> The Relation of <hi>Keinton</hi> Battell, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Secretary <hi>Nicholas</hi> his Letters to Forraigne States, ſtuft with the groſſeſt and moſt apparent lyes that ever were heard, <hi>As that Colonell</hi> Haſtings <hi>came to</hi> Lichfield <hi>and drave thence the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Forces, and reſcued the Earle of</hi> Cheſterfield, <hi>when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Forces yet poſſeſſe the Towne, and the Earle is the Parliaments pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner: And that the Lord</hi> Brooke <hi>was Armed</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>throughout with Armour of proofe when hee was ſlaine by a ſhot in the eye,</hi> and upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of thoſe that were preſent with him at his death, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that he had no Armour on at all but his Head-peece: <hi>That M.</hi> Marſhall <hi>the Divine was madde, and cried out he was damned, and M.</hi> Caſe <hi>adminiſtring the Sacrament, invited ſuch only as had contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Parliament,</hi> and ſuch dung-hill ſtuffe, ſavouring of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of him that was a lyer from the beginning; <hi>by their fruits you may know them.</hi> I forbeare to inſtance in many others as groundleſſe as theſe. And who doe truly informe and diſabuſe the people? theſe men that publiſh theſe things for the King, and under his Name, and in abuſe thereof, or the Parliament, which hath ſet forth nothing, but what upon full examination is diſcovered, let the World judge. And we are confident, the Parliament hath not impriſoned any for prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any thing but what was diſhonourable to his Majeſty, and falſe and ſcandalous to the Higheſt Court, and that is Legall, reaſonable and neceſſary.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:111268:15"/>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Sixtly, he ſaith, <hi>That the Moneyes advanced by gift or adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Act of Parliament, and Souldiers preſſed for</hi> Ireland <hi>to reduce the Rebells there, the Parliament hath diverted to maintaine an unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Warre in</hi> England, <hi>ſo they doe viſibly loſe the Kingdome of</hi> Ireland, <hi>that they may be the better inabled to loſe the Kingdome of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> The War in our Kingdome, we conceive is unnaturall in the offending party that firſt raiſed Armes, and not in the party defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or Parliament; to defend againſt unjuſt violence as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth is naturall, to purſue and endeavour by force to bring De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to Juſtice, that reſiſt the Proceſſe of the Courts of Juſtice, as the Parliament doth, is naturall and juſt by all Laws of God, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Nations, and our Municipall Laws, and the maintenance of War is of like nature as the War is. And if any perſon or thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for <hi>Ireland</hi> hath been taken and uſed by the Parliament, it hath been for a time only, and that alſo inforced by this unnaturall War, to ſave <hi>England,</hi> without which <hi>Ireland</hi> cannot ſtand, and is repaid and returned to the uſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> againe with great advantage, as by the accouts thereof cleerely appeares. And who loſes <hi>Ireland?</hi> The Parliament, which continually ſends them all the aide and help they can or can procure, or the Evill Councellours about the King, that ſeduce him to take away the Horſes and other things prepared for the Traine of Artillery ſent thitherward by the Parliament, and divers loades of Cloathes and ſuites of Apparrell bought by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſent unto the Souldiers there, for which no colour of ſatisfaction hath been given to poore <hi>Ireland</hi> to this day? And who alſo withheld the King from giving his Royall aſſent to the Bill of Tonnage and Poundage, thereby as much as in them lyes, to hinder all defence of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and by conſequence, laying open all wayes of ſupplying the Rebells there, with all neceſſaries for the War, and for their ſupport from Forraigne parts? And who alſo put the King upon this unnaturall War, whereby <hi>England</hi> is ſpoiled and deſtroyed, and the Parliament diſabled to raiſe meanes to preſerve and defend that Kingdome? Who have drawne over the Commanders imployed by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111268:16"/> the Parliament againſt the Rebells of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to foment this unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall War, and to devoure us, and lay waſt this goodly Kingdome, as Captaine <hi>Boteler,</hi> and 14 other with him lately, and others at other times formerly.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Seventhly, he ſaith, <hi>That the Houſe of Commons have ſhewed themſelves averſe from peace, that they have Voted there ſhall be no C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Armes, leaſt by a free Treaty a peace might enſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Our Bretheren of <hi>Scotland</hi> did treat for peace without ſuch Ceſſation, and with good ſucceſſe. And though the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons did once Vote there ſhould be no Ceſſation of Armes, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then in order to a disbanding, in their wiſedomes fore-ſeeing that it would be abuſed, and prove full of ſnares to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as it hath ſince proved; yet through our importunity, they were induced to give way to a Ceſſation of Armes in order to the Treaty alſo. And now we find by experience, the Reſolution which when they were their own, and not drawn aſide by our importunity, and by a deſire to hold a concurrence with the Lords, they tooke up was grounded upon wiſedome, and cleerely the beſt, for after much time ſpent about it, both the King and they are faine to give it over, and goe on upon the Treaty without it. And we now alſo diſcerne, that they deſired the beſt way for us at firſt, and which would bring on an effectuall Ceſſation and full peace, namely that all Armies ſhould be disbanded, and that that ſhould be the firſt of their Propoſitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and executed before any other. And to facilitate the way thereof, they have yeelded ſo fully to the Kings deſire in his firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition about his Revenue, Navy, Fortes and Portes, as can with any colour of reaſon be deſired, to reſigne them all unto him, onely deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, That ſeeing himſelfe cannot in Perſon mannage them, he will put them into ſuch hands to be named by himſelfe as his people may confide in. This ſo evidently diſcovers and ſatisfies us of their deſire of peace, as nothing can doe it more fully, more cleerly, and after ſuch disbanding, the Treaty may goe on concerning all other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the King and his great and faithfull Councell in a Parliamentary way, when the Kingdome ſhall be eaſed of the intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111268:16"/> burdens of the many great Armies that are now on foot in the bowels of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> And this Libeller further bequarrels the carriage of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards the Subject, Thus, firſt he ſaith, <hi>They have made an Ordinance that the twentith part of mens eſtates muſt be paid towards the maintenance of this warre, and appointeth who ſhall value it, and then Collectours to diſtraine for it, and ſell the diſtreſſe and impriſon the perſon that will not pay it, if no distreſſe can be found, and their families baniſhed from their habitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Firſt, This is nothing to what is done in the Kings Name, by them that ſeduce him by their evill Councell, who inforce many Subjects unto contribution, farre ſurmounting this, and plunder and deſtroy them if they pay it not, and take from others all they have without meaſure or mercy, and drive them from their habitation, that if the places under the Parliaments protection were not a refuge unto them, they muſt utterly periſh with all that depend upon them, and ſeiſe upon the perſons of others that never oppoſed them, and uſe them with more cruelty and inhumanity then they do their beaſts, meerly to make a bragging ſhew of a great victory by many priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and all againſt the <hi>Knowne Laws,</hi> to which his Majeſty hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven quickning by his perſonall Royall aſſent.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Ordinance mentioned is by this lying tongue that cannot ſpeak truth ſlandered, as if it inforced the paiment of the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith part; when in truth it binds the Aſſeſſours not to aſcend in their Aſſeſſment above the twentith part of any mans eſtate, leaving them power to deſcend to a leſſe proportion, and no man that loves his Country will ſticke upon ſo ſmall a contribution for the maintenance of our Religion and Liberties, againſt the hand of violence and foot of pride, lift up by the Cavaleers to the deſtruction of them all.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Secondly, He ſaith, <hi>That leaſt the Parliament ſhould not have the colour of Law ſufficient to blind the world, they have lately made an Ordinance for the Inhabitantes of</hi> Northampton, Rutland, Derby, <hi>&amp;c. to pay and to be aſſeſſed by Aſſeſſours named in their Act, in imitation of the Statute lately made for the</hi> 400000<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>. <hi>and this as is probable ſhall be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the whole Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:111268:17"/>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We conceive it very fit, juſt and legall, that all ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the ſaving of all. It is neceſſary the power and priviledges of Parliament be maintained, or elſe farewell Religion, Liberty, property and all, and we ſhall fall into the like miſery as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>France</hi> have ever been, ſithence their Kings over-powred their Parliaments, and deſtroyed them, which <hi>Forteſcue</hi> in the 35. Chapter of his booke of our Laws, ſets forth. And the Parliament for the preſervation of the Kingdome may doe, and have done grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters then this, as our Hiſtories plainly ſhew, and if any be ſo impious as not to be willing to ſave their country, it is fit they ſhould be enforced unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Thirdly, He ſaith, <hi>The Parliament hath yet a ſhorter and aſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer way, where they underſtand there is any mony, plate or goods to be had, they ſend a party of Horſe or other strength to fetch it, as out of an Enemies Country, becauſe the owners are good Subjects to the King, or they ſuſpect them to be ſo, and that alone is crime ſufficient to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them, or judge them, or take execution upon them, and all this without the Ceremony of Law by their abſolute and omnipotent power, which cannot erre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If this lyar had inſtanced in any particular, it would have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, that ſuch as have been ſo uſed have been ſo farre off from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good Subjects, as they have bin manifeſt Traitors to their country, and fomenters of the preſent unnaturall war: and if any be found and judged to be ſo in the higheſt Court, by that Court it may be legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done without other Ceremonies of Law, neceſſary in inferiour Courts. And this power is and ever hath been in the Parliament, when the thing is neceſſary for the publike Defence and ſafety of the Kingdome, and ſo judged by them, whoſe Repreſentatives and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees they are, in caſe where the King is ſeduced by wicked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels to endeavour the deſtruction of the Parliament, which hath bin the deſigne of ſuch Counſellours ever ſince the King came to the Crowne, as clearely appears to every judicious obſerver of the times and proceedings at Court. Others of inferiour power have done it, as we ſee in <hi>Heburnes</hi> caſe before, and judged lawfull, but that the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111268:17"/> Parliament cannot erre, was never challenged, and is here maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wickedly added, to render the Parliament odious, which is the main ſcope of this Libeller; and for their Omnipotency, though it hath been a Proverbe among the learned of our Lawes, that <hi>Parliamentum omnia potest,</hi> yet the Parliament hath never chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged any power, but for the publike good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fourthly, He ſaith, <hi>The Houſe of Commons diſcharges Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Servants from their Maſters ſervice without the conſent of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Dames, and either perſwades or compels them to ſerve in their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Firſt, It is falſe that the Parliament hath compelled any to ſerve them in their Army. Secondly, It is falſe that the Houſe of Commons alone have done this, as appeares by the <hi>Ordinance</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, <hi>November,</hi> 1642. And what the Parliament hath perſwaded in this is very juſt; the publike Relation of Apprentices to the ſafety of the Kingdom, being more to be reſpected then their private Relation to their Maſters and Dames, who partake in the publike benefit of the ſervice in the wane, which tends to the ſaving of them and all they have among the reſt intereſſed with them in the publike ſafetie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fiftly, He ſaith, <hi>That the Parliament hath impriſoned ſome for Petitioning, and ſome for intending to Petition unto them, as if that alone were a cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e, if the matter of the Petition doe not flatter them in their preſent courſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We know they have been ſo ſarre from accounting Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a crime, as they have received multitudes of Petitions from all parts of the Kingdome. This therefore is a falſe imputation, but when the matter of the Petition hath been ſeditious and tending to the diſturbance of the publike peace, and ſtuff with unjuſt aſperſions of the Parliament, in ſuch caſe only they have impriſoned the <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> as is moſt juſt and neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Sixthly, Hee averres, <hi>That the Houſe of Commons have impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned others for Petitioning and intending to Petition to the King, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111268:18"/> yet the way is open to Heaven, and GOD will heare in his good time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> They never impriſoned any for <hi>Petitioning</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> except the matter were, as is above-ſaid, to foment diviſion between the King and his people. And ſuch a malicious Libellers petitioning Heaven, will find no acceptance, for <hi>the prayer of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord:</hi> And if ſuch Petitions be offered to Heaven, as have been to the Parliament or to his Majeſty by ſuch ſpirits as this Malignant is poſſeſſed withall, God will impriſon ſuch Petitioners, except they repent in another-geſſe priſon then the Parliament caſts them into.</p>
            <p>And concerning priviledges of Parliament this Libeller proceeds thus.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Firſt, <hi>That the Parliament forbids us to diſpute their Priviledges, and aſſumes the ſole judgement of them, when in former ages they might be and have been judged by the Lawes of the Kingdome, but he admits the Parliament to be Iudges of offences committed by their owne members againſt the Houſes, and of the election of their members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> We know and have found by late experience; that when any inferiour Court hath preſumed to diſpute and determine the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Parliament, which is the higheſt Court, they have been puniſhed for it by the Parliament. Have the inferiour Courts of <hi>London</hi> or other places, been ever admitted to judge or determine the priviledges of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> or <hi>Common-pleas,</hi> we cannot conceive it to be reaſonable or legall; but this Libellers malice hath ſo blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, as he raves like a mad-man againſt the Parliament, publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to their prejudice, though never ſo much againſt cleare reaſon and common experience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Secondly, He ſaith, <hi>Some of the members of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have bin committed or put out of the Houſe for ſpeaking freely againſt the ſenſe of the Houſe, or rather of ſome members therof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> This we are very confident is a loud lie, and if he had inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in any one, it would have bin as manifeſt as the Sun, when it ſhines out in its might and ſtrength to be a lie. And it is altogether impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111268:18"/> that the whole Houſe ſhould deale ſo with any member for ſpeaking againſt the ſenſe of ſome members therof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Thirdly, He ſaith, <hi>The priviledges of the Houſe of Commons were never challenged till now, to extend to any member which ſhould commit treaſon or fellony. But they have now declared, that no member of the Houſe, nor other imployed by them ſhall be queſtioned for Treaſon but in Parliament, or at least by leave of the Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> It is true, no priviledge of Parliament doth extend, or was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver challenged to extend to exempt any member of Parliament from being queſtioned for treaſon or felony, but it hath bin ever challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and is an undoubted priviledge of Parliament, that none of their members upon a bare accuſation of theſe crimes ſhould be left to a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall tryall, before the Houſe, wherof he is a member, be ſatisfied that there is good ground for the accuſation; upon a meere accuſation no man is to looſe his priviledge of Parliament, but upon reall cauſe. If to accuſe be ſufficient, who ſhall be innocent? and if the Law were otherwiſe, every man that ſpeaks his mind legally and according to his conſcience, and the truſt repoſed in him by his Country for the publike good, if the King like it not he ſhall be preſently accuſed of treaſon by the Attorney Generall, and thereby taken out of the Houſe, and ſo freedome of ſpeech in Parliament will be utterly loſt, and all members of Parliament that are good Patriots and ſtand for our Religion, Lawes, or Liberties may be taken out of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and none left there, but ſuch as will ſerve the times, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour the evill Councellours about the King, a high-way to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and blow up, not as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> intended in the Powder-plot one Parliament, but all Parliaments, and overthrow the Kingdome and reduce us and our poſterity to ſlavery and miſery without reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for by the ſame reaſon, as one man ſhall looſe his priviledge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch an accuſation, twenty, an hundred and more may, and then farewell the liberty and happineſſe of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Houſe of Commons have ever proceeded juſtly and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt their owne members, where there hath been reall cauſe to put them out of the Houſe, and deliver them over to the hand of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111268:19"/> Juſtice, but if they ſhould doe it upon a meere accuſation, yea ſuch an accuſation as is aſhamed to be tryed (as the late accuſation of the five Members, which would never endure the mentioning of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.) Certainly they ſhould doe apparant injury and injuſtice and betray the truſt committed to them, and they that had a hand in this more then Gun-powder plot, counſelling and endeavouring by that devilliſh deſigne againſt the Parliament will remain infamous to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fourthly, He ſaith, <hi>The Houſe of Commons have made a cloſe Committee, wherein a very few members of that Houſe are privy to their counſels, and what thoſe few conclude is ſummarily reported to the Houſe, and that taken up upon trust by an implicite faith of all the rest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> This we know to be falſe in the whole, and in every part of it. Firſt, The Houſe of Commons alone hath not made any ſuch Committee, but that Committee is made by common conſent of both Houſes, and conſiſts of Members of both Houſes, and is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the preparing of buſineſſe for the Houſe, and for the quicker diſpatch of the affaires of the Houſe, as all know that underſtand any thing of the proceedings of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It conſiſteth not of a very few, but of a competent and fit number for ſuch a Committee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Not only the members of the Houſe of Commons, but of the Houſe of Peers alſo are privy to the councels thereof.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The reports from that Committee to either or both Houſes are as of other Committees, nothing in it taken upon impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit faith, but as every member of either Houſe is at liberty to be at the councels, debates and reſults thereof, if they pleaſe; ſo the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reaſons, warrants and grounds of the Report, are by the Repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter clearly opened, and if not, every member may require an account therof before he give his Vote.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Fiftly, He ſaith, <hi>Many of the preſent members of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have had their elections queſtioned, and in two years ſpace have had no leiſure to determine them, if they incline to the poſitions they lay down, least they ſhould looſe ſuch from their party.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111268:19"/>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> If this Libeller had inſtanced in particulars, an anſwer might be particularly given thereunto, and he convinced of his forged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, but to a generall charge we can ſay thus much in generall, That all queſtions concerning election that have been brought to the Houſe from the Committee of Elections have bin preſently upon the Report thereof determined. But if the Committee hath not had lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſit or opportunity to report, becauſe of the great obſtructions that have been by the enemies of the publike good, caſt in the way of the Parliaments proceedings, and the Houſe of Commons enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſpend all their time to reſiſt, and to endeavour to remoove the ſame, it is not the fault of the Parliament, but the fault of theſe men of <hi>Beliall</hi> that are riſen up againſt the Parliament and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Sixtly, He ſaith, <hi>That when a matter of Importance hath beene in debate and put to the question, and thereupon determined, the ſame queſtion hath been again reſumed at another time better prepared for the purpoſe, and determined quite contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Sol.</label> Firſt, That any ſuch queſtion hath bin received after determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that hath not come into the Houſe upon ſome new occaſion inforcing it, we doe not beleeve to be true, but that a great Councell upon debate determines one time one way, and upon better prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſecond thoughts, when it is by ſome emergent occaſion brought againe into debate, conclude another way, and quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is no newes, it being both the priviledge and property of wiſe men to change their opinions upon better, further and more mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration and conſideration, being better prepared for it, then they could be at firſt, when it was ſuddenly and unexpectedly moved, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated and determined.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, he quarrells at the Statute by which this Parliament is fixed ſo as it cannot be diſſolved without common conſent of the King and both Houſes, which in truth is a Statute onely declaratory of the Common Law of this Kingdome, and no Parliament neither can or ought to be diſſolved, till they have redreſſed all the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the Kingdome. This wretch in this diſcovers a heart full of poyſon againſt the publike good, that like the raging Sea ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111268:20"/> out nothing but mire and dirt, and foming out his own ſhame. A Law made by the Supreame power of this Kingdome, the Three Eſtates, cannot eſcape the virulent tongue of this <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> If this Law may be ſpoken againſt or queſtioned, all others may. And whereas the King in almoſt all his Declarations, proteſts he likes well of, and will obſerve and maintaine all the Laws made this Parliament, this Villaine forbeares not to ſay he was over-reached in it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, he reckons up the miſeries of a Civill War, and ſaith, that the Parliament is the cauſe of it, when all men that have obſerved the Hiſtory and Acts of theſe times, knowes well at whoſe doores that ſin and miſchiefellies, and whom it calls Father.</p>
            <p>And he deſires amendment of what is amiſſe, without plucking up the foundation of government intended to be pluckt up, except he meane the government by that Officer whom we call Biſhop, which never appeared in holy Scriptures, but in the perſon of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> which the Parliament deſires to remove, that the ſame may be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the government of the Church by Presbiters, the Officers and Biſhops which the Scriptures approve of, and give the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church unto, we know not what he meanes by founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of government, and we (as we conceive all good men alſo doe) doe for our parts deſire to have a Church government according to the will of God expreſſed in his word, and not according to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of his profeſſed Arch Enemy expreſſed in the Popiſh Hierarchy.</p>
            <p>And we are confident, that the Parliament had long before this by their judgement and wiſdome, provided for and ſetled our Religion according to God, which is the true and indeed onely honour of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the greateſt ſatisfaction to our conſciences, if they might have had their wills, and if it were obtained, would procure mercy from Heaven, that the Sword ſhould be ſheathed and devoure no more fleſh, and our Lives, Eſtates and Liberties be preſerved, which are onely ſecured by our walking according to the Rule, the only way in which the Angells will attend us, and all happinſſe flow upon us and our Poſterity for ever.</p>
            <p>And as for burying of by-paſt Actions in an act of Oblivion, we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111268:20"/> are confident the Parliament neither needs nor deſires it for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nor their friends, being conſcious of nothing done by them for which they have cauſe to feare the hand of Juſtice, and if the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable peace which they now ſo ſincerely ſeeke and deſire ſhall not be obtained, we proteſt to all the world, that with the utmoſt hazard of our lives and fortunes and of all we can call ours, we will endeavour to vindicate them and our ſelves, from the barbarous, inhumane, and more then Turkiſh and Heatheniſh Tyrannies of the Evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours about the King, which ſeduce him, and their Cavaleres, and we doubt not but our God in whom we truſt, who hath wrought great ſalvations and done great things for us ſince the beginning of this unhappy War, will be our guide and our ſtrength, and fight our battells, and goe before us as a devouring fire to conſume the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Peace and his Glory, and perfect the worke of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo happily begun and wonderfully carried on hitherto in ſpight of all oppoſition and in the ſight of them that hate him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
